export default Citizenship_Model_2015 = [
  {
    id: "h1",
    Number_of_Questions: "60 Questions",
    Time_Allowed: "1 hour"
  },
  {
    id: 'h2',
    header1: " ADDIS ABABA CITY ADMINISTRATION EDUCATION BUREAU GRADE 8 Citizenship MODEL EXAMINATIONS 2015 E.C/2023G.C"},
  {
    id: "I",
    header1: "I. READ THE FOLLOWING QUESTIONS CAREFULLY AND CHOOSE THE CORRECT ALTERNATIVE ANSWER FOR THE FOLLOWING QUESTIONS",
     },
    {
    id: 1,
    question: "____________ is concerned with the development of one’s character in order to prepare one for good citizenship.",
    options: [" Vice Ethics", "Virtue ethics", "Immorality", "Dishonesty"],
    correct_option: "Virtue ethics",
    explanation:"virtue ethics is a branch of ethics developed primarily by Aristotle and other ancient Greek"+
    " virtues in determining the rightness of an action, as opposed to approaches that emphasise duties or rules or the consequences of actions."
     },
  {
    id: 2,
    question: "The study of what is good and bad ends to pursue in life, as well as what is right and wrong to do in daily life, is known as __________ ",
    options: ["Civics", "Vice Ethics", "Ethics","Honesty"],
    correct_option: "Ethics",
    explanation:"The study of what good and bad ends to pursue in life, as well as what is right and wrong to do in daily life, is known as ethics."+
    " It is the creation of reasonable standards and procedures for making ethical decisions."
  },
  {
    id: 3,
    question: "The first step in Ethical decision making is:",
    options: ["Identify the central ethical problem", ". Identify stakeholders and their interests","Find a possible solution to the dilemma","All are correct answers"],
    correct_option: "Identify the central ethical problem",
    explanation:"There are five simple and inseparable steps to solving an ethical problem. \n" +
    
    "1. Identify the central ethical problem  \n"+
    
    "2. Identify stakeholders and their interests: \n"+
        
    "3. Find a possible solution to the dilemma: \n"+
    "4. Evaluate each solution: \n"+
    
    "5. Select and justify the solution that best solves the dilemma: \n"     
  },
  {
    id: 4,
    question: "Moral virtue includes all EXCEPT_________",
    options: ["Paying fair tax", "Generosity",
     "Self-discipline", "All are correct answers"],
    correct_option: "All are correct answers",
    explanation:"Moral virtues:refers to behaviours that allow a person to live reasonably in his or her community, region, or world."+
    " Moral virtues are dispositions that allow a person to live in accordance with their values."
  },
  {
    id: 5,
    question: "A citizen’s generosity is measured by the extent to which he or she is willing to work for the benefit of both individuals and society as a whole. This can be designated by:",
    options: ["Moral virtue", "Prudence", "Courage", " Civic virtue"],
    correct_option: "Moral virtue",
    explanation:"Generosity is defined as a moral disposition to expend time, effort, and resources for the benefit of others."+ 
    " The virtuous citizen is gen-erous to others and the community as a whole. It is the quality of being kind and understanding, as well as the willingness to give"+
    " others valuable things that is frequently defined as an act of self-lessness."
    
  },
  
  {
    id: 6,
    question: "The importance of virtue ethics includes that:",
    options: ['It helps one to distinguish between right and wrong', 'It helps in finding out the true purpose of life', ' It helps in building a positive approach to things', 'All are correct answers'],
    correct_option: "All are correct answers",
    explanation:"virtue ethics is important: \n"+
    "It helps one to distinguish between right and wrong: \n"+
    "Enables to become responsible and contributing members in the society: \n"+
    "It helps in finding out the true purpose of life: \n"+
    "It also helps in building a positive approach to things:  \n"+
    "It helps to eliminate problems of social evils from one’s life"
  },
  {
    id: 7,
    question: "Which of the following is true regarding fairness:",
    options: ["It is a method of evaluating people or situations that is free of bias.", "It is the ability to make judgments that are general rather than concrete and specific to a particular case", "It is fair if the reward is only given based on a person’s characteristics", "Only B and C are correct answers"],
    correct_option: "It is a method of evaluating people or situations that is free of bias",
    explanation:"Fairness: is frequently defined as a method of evaluating people or situations that is free of bias."
  },
  {
    id: 8,
    question: "It is difficult to acquire morale virtue through ______________",
    options: [" Learning", "Naturally", "Practice", " Imitation"],
    correct_option: "Naturally",
    explanation:"Moral virtue does not come naturally to us."+ 
    "Moral virtues are habits that we develop through practice and imitation of exceptionally virtuous people or especially virtuous actions."
  },
  {
    id: 9,
    question: "Which of the following is NOT true about virtue Ethics?",
    options: ["Acting and behaving in accordance with certain acceptable standards", "Willing to work for the benefit of both individuals and society ", "Fairness means everyone receives and shares exactly the same thing", "All are correct answers"],
    correct_option: "Fairness means everyone receives and shares exactly the same thing",
    explanation:"virtue ethics is a branch of ethics developed primarily by Aristotle and other ancient Greek"+
    " virtues in determining the rightness of an action, as opposed to approaches that emphasise duties or rules or the consequences of actions."
     },
  {
    id: 10,
    question: "Among the following, which one is the consequence of dishonesty?",
    options: ["Results in respect among friends and the community", "Erodes trust among friends and the community.", "An honest person earns a good status among the community.", " It is one of the best compliments a person can receive."],
    correct_option: "Erodes trust among friends and the community.",
    explanation:"dishonesty is a lack of honesty is a way for disaster."
     },
  {
    id: 11,
    question: ". What is the importance of paying fair tax?",
    options: ["Allows the government to carry out its functions", "Hindering the development of the country", "Aggravate corruption", "Courage social evil"],
    correct_option: "Allows the government to carry out its functions",
    explanation:"paying fair taxes as a member of society is one of the responsibilities and obligations of a good citi-zen."+
    " Paying taxes allows the government to carry out its functions. As a result, every member of society must contribute to"+
    " the government’s support. "
  },
  {
    id: 12,
    question: "What is courage?",
    options: ["It is the ability to objectively examine the potential consequences of your actions", "It is the determination to work hard despite any obstacles that may exist", "It is opposing rule of law", "It is distracting common goods"],
    correct_option: "It is the determination to work hard despite any obstacles that may exist",
    explanation:"Courage is the attitude of confronting and dealing with what is perceived to be difficult or painful rather than avoiding it; it is a " +
    " quality of being fearless or brave. It means trying again and again until you succeed."
  },
  {
    id: 13,
    question: "What is prudence?",
    options: ["Evolves behaving in accordance with certain acceptable standards.", "It is the ability to objectively examine the potential consequences of your actions", "It is the determination to work hard despite any obstacles that may exist", "All are correct answers"],
    correct_option: "It is the ability to objectively examine the potential consequences of your actions",
    explanation:"Prudence is the ability to make sound decisions in order to avoid danger or risk."+ 
    " It is an act of care, caution, and good judgement,as well as foresight. "+
    " It entails exercising caution in your decisions and pausing to reflect before acting. "
  },
{
 id: 14,
    question: "Unitary, Federal and Confederal are:",
    options: ["System of government", "Forms of government",
     "State structure", "Instruments of government"],
    correct_option: "State structure",
    explanation:"The concept of state structure is concerned with whether power is constitutionally devolved to lower administrative units or monopolized centrally by national governments."+
       "There are three types of state structures in the world: unitary, federal, and confederal."
  },

    {
    id: 15,
    question: "Which one is correct regarding unitary state structure?",
    options: ["Characterized by power centralization", "May involve separation of executive, legislative, and judicial powers",
      "May delegate such powers to a subordinate unit","All are correct answers."],
    correct_option: "Characterized by power centralization",
    explanation:"The unitary state is a type of state structure character-ized by power centralization. "+ 
    " It is a type of state structur in which a single power, known as the central govern-ment, controls all aspects of government."
  },
    {
    id: 16,
    question: "Corruption can be found in the form of:",
    options: ["Bribery", "Nepotism", "Embezzlement", "All are correct answers"],
    correct_option: "All are correct answers",
    explanation:"Corruption occurs within the private and public health sectors and may appear as theft, embezzlement, nepotism, bribery"
  },
  {
    id: 17,
    question: "Which of the following is correct about state structure?",
    options: ["Confederal arrangement is a guarantee of democracy", "Being federal is not a guarantee of democracy.", "There are unitary states that have democracy", 
"B and C are correct answers"],
    correct_option: "B and C are correct answers",
    explanation:"Confederal arrangement is not a guarantee of democracy: A confederal arrangement typically involves independent states forming an alliance, and it doesn't necessarily guarantee democracy."+
    " Some confederations may have democratic principles, but the confederal structure itself doesn't guarantee democracy."+
    "Being federal is not a guarantee of democracy: This statement is true. While many federal states have democratic systems, "+
    "the federal structure itself does not guarantee democracy. There have been federal states with authoritarian regimes."+
   "There are unitary states that have democracy: This statement is true. Unitary states can indeed have democratic systems."+
   "The presence of a unitary structure doesn't preclude democracy."
  },
  {
    id: 18,
    question: "Countries with heterogeneous society’s prefer_________ state structures",
    options: ["Unitary", "Federal", "Centralized"," All are correct answers"],
    correct_option: " Federal",
    explanation:"federalism allows different groups to share power over common interests."+ 
    " It allows different groups of people in different parts of the country to enjoy diversity." +
    " Thus, territorially large countries with diverse societies prefer federalism."+ 
    " Except for China, the majority of large countries use a federal state structure."
        },
  {
    id: 19,
    question: "Which of the following are federal states?",
    options: ["Ethiopia, India and Canada", "China and skilanka", " France and Kenya", "Italy and UK"],
    correct_option: "Ethiopia, Nigeria, and Canada",
    explanation:"in terms of usage, one-third of the world’s population is governed by states with some form of federal structure."+
     " The United States, Brazil, Pakistan, Australia, Mexico, Switzerland, Canada, Nigeria, and Ethiopia are among these countries."
        },
  {
    id: 20,
    question: "Limitations of unitary states are:",
    options: ["Concentration of Power", "Miss use of power",
     "None recognition of local diversities", "All are correct answers"],
    correct_option: "All are correct answers",
    explanation:"Limitations of unitary states are \n"+ 
    "Concentration of Power \n"+
    "Miss use of power \n"+
    "None recognition of local diversities"
  },
  {
    id: 21,
    question: "The function of federal states in Ethiopia includes all EXCEPT?",
    options: ["Establish and control The National Defense Force.", " Formulate and implement Foreign policy"," Organize local police force"," Printing National currency"],
    correct_option: "Organize local police force",
    explanation:"Organizing local police force is the function of regional government"
  },

   {
    id: 22,
    question: "When a group of people or nations form an alliance what type of state is Formed?",
    options: ["Confederal state arrangement","Regional state","Federal state ","Unitary state"],
    correct_option: "Confederal state arrangement",
    explanation:"A confederation is formed when a group of people or nations form an alliance."+ 
    "It allows each member to govern it while voluntarily agreeing to collaborate on common goals."
},
{
    id: 23,
    question: "The form of government that exists during the Emperor regime was:",
    options: ["The military system","Monarchical system ","Parliamentary system","Democratic system"],
    correct_option: "Monarchical system",
    explanation:"The imperial system has existed until the 1974 in the country."+
    "The imperial form of government was Monarchical with absolutist and centralized administration."+
    " Its was Power was transferred for descendents of the emperor."+
     "In line to this, the 1931 constitution of Ethiopia article 4 states that ‘the throne and the crown of the"+
    "empire shall be transmitted to descendents of the Emperor pursuant to the law of the imperial house’."
},
{
    id: 24,
    question: "The form of government that exists during the Derg regime was ",
    options: ["The military regime","Monarchical Regimes","parliamentary system","Democratic system"],
    correct_option: "The military regime",
    explanation:"the Derg regime was has military and has the following features \n"+
    " Emerged to be military and dictatorial form of government in Ethiopia. \n"+
    " Adopted unitary state structure. \n"+
          "Replaced feudalism and monarchical systems by socialism and presidential systems of government respectively. \n"+
          "Ended ancestral power succession to descents of the emperors. \n"+
    "The working class became the sovereign power possessor by forming unicameral chambered parliament named as National Shengo.\n"+
          "The president was the head of state and commander —in-chief of the national army."
},
{
    id: 25,
    question: "What are the disadvantages of federalism?",
    options: ["Confusion and conflict of laws","Duplication of resource and system."," Recognition of local diversities","A and B are correct answers"],
    correct_option: "A and B are correct answers",
    explanation:"disadvantages of federalism are: \n"+
  " deficiency of authority over constituent states and individual citizens \n"+
  "unfit for a state without geographic continuity \n"+
      "confusion and conflict of laws \n"+
      "affects the of power of legislation at the central unit on subjects that need uniform legislation \n"+
      "expenses and dalliance due to its duplicated system of legislation and administration \n"
},
{
  id: 26,
  question: "Presidential system can be governments when,",
  options: ["Executive and legislative branches of government separately elected by the people","Executive is selected from the legislature","The prime minister is elected by indirect vote","All are correct answers"],
  correct_option: "Executive and legislative branches of government separately elected by the people",
  explanation:"The presidential system of government is a form of government in which the president serves as the head of state and government. \n"+
  " The president and legislature are directly elected by the people and answer to them."
},
{
  id: 27,
  question: " What are the features of parliamentary system?",
  options: ["Nominal head of state is the priesdant","The real executive authority is held by the prime minister. ","The real executive authority is held by the president","The president is the “true working head of the state."],
  correct_option: "The real executive authority is held by the prime minister",
  explanation:"Features of Parliamentary System are: \n"+
  "The real executive authority is held by the prime minister. \n"+
  "Nominally, the head of state, whether a monarch or a president, has authority \n"+
  "Political homogeneity: \n"+
  "Collective responsibility:"
},
{
  id: 28,
  question: "What is the INCORRECT relationship between state and government?",
  options: ["All people who live in a state are subject to the government","Government is responsible for achieving all of a state’s objectives","Government is an element of the state.","In the absence of government, the state can exist"],
  correct_option: "All people who live in a state are subject to the government",
  explanation:"State and government are so closely related in political discourse. Hence, they are frequently used interchangeably."+
  "However, they are diametrically opposed concepts."+
  "In the absence of government, state cannot exist;"+
  " Government is not only one of the elements, but the most important one."+
  " Government is responsible for achieving all of a state’s objectives."+
  "All people who live in a state are subject to the state’s jurisdiction"+
  "The state provides legitimacy to the government, and the government makes the state a reality"
},
{
  id: 29,
  question: "Which of the following is correct regarding the Derg regime?",
  options: ["Redistribution of land to the tiller"," Campaigning of literacy"," Respecting of religious difference","A and B are correct answers"],
  correct_option: "A and B are correct answers",
  explanation:"During the Derg regime Land redistribution to tillers and literacy campaigns were among critical successes"
},
{
  id: 30,
  question: "Which of the following is the feature of Parliamentarian system?",
  options: [" Superior position of president","Separation of powers","Principle of checks and balances","Collective responsibility"],
  correct_option: "Collective responsibility",
  explanation:"Features of Parliamentary System are: \n"+
  "The real executive authority is held by the prime minister. \n"+
  "Nominally, the head of state, whether a monarch or a president, has authority \n"+
  "Political homogeneity: \n"+
  "Collective responsibility:"
},
{
  id:31,
  question: "The post 1991 government characterized by:",
  options: ["The right of self determination","Land redistribution to tiller","State formation","B and C are correct answers"],
  correct_option: "State formation",
  explanation:""
},
{
  id:32,
  question: "______is a political system in which the people hold supreme political  Power",
  options: ["Monarchy","Military dictator ship"," Democracy","Anarchy"],
  correct_option: "Democracy",
  explanation:"democracy is a political system in which the people hold supreme political power."
},
{
  id: 33,
  question: "Which of the following is NOT principle of democracy?",
  options: ["Single-Party System","Respect for Human Rights","The principle of secularism","The principle of popular sovereignty"],
  correct_option: "Single-Party System",
  explanation:"principle of democracy are:"+
  "Popular sovereignty: \n"+
  "Supremacy of constitution \n"+
  " Citizen Participation  \n"+
  "Separation of power  \n"+
  "The principle of secularism \n"+
  "The principle of accountability and transparency  \n"+
  "Respect for Human Rights \n"+
  "Multi-Party System \n"+
  "The Rule of Law"
},
{
  id:34,
  question: "The most important aspect of secularism is________",
  options: ["Separation of government organs","Separation of state and religion","Fusion of government organs","Fusion of state and religion"],
  correct_option: "separation of state and religion",
  explanation:"State and religion are separate. \n"+
 "Article 11 Separation of State relagion \n"+
  "The state shall not interfere in religious matters and religion shall mot imterfere in state affairs, and Religion"
},
{
  id:35,
  question: "When a country has only one political party, the result is _________",
  options: ["Semi-democracy and semi- dictatorship","Democracy","Dictatorship"," Liberalism "],
  correct_option: "Dictatorship",
  explanation:"hen a country only has one political party, the result is a dictatorship."
},
{
  id:36,
  question: "The government organ of the state which is responsible to interpret the law is _______",
  options: ["The legislative branch of the government","The executive branch of the government","The judiciary branch of the government","The house of federation"],
  correct_option: "The judiciary branch of the government",
  explanation:"Government is made up of legislative,executive, and judicial branches. \n"+ 
  "The legislative organ of the state creates laws, the executive implements them,"+ 
  " and the judiciary applies them to specific cases arising from a violation of the law"
},
{
  id:37,
  question: "Civility includes:",
  options: ["Respecting one another and honoring differences","Listening and seeking common ground","Tolerance, acceptance, and non-discrimination"," All are correct answers"],
  correct_option: "All are correct answers",
  explanation:"civility is a moral obligation that people owe to one another. \n"+
  "Respecting one another and honoring differences \n"+
  "Listening and seeking common ground \n"+
      "Engaging in social discourse and appreciating its relevance \n"+
  "Attention to bodily hygiene, dress, interactions, and physical conduct \n"+
  "Fundamental good manners for legislative bodies \n"+
  "Tolerance, acceptance, and non-discrimination."
},
{
  id: 38,
  question: "Among the following which one is the Challenges of democracy in Ethiopia?",
  options: ["Lack of an informed society","Massive investments in infrastructure","The reforms of democratic institutions","Paving platform of discussion for political parties"],
  correct_option: "Lack of an informed society",
  explanation:"challenges of democracy in Ethiopia are: \n"+
  "There are no powerful institutions to support democratic processes \n"+
  "The absence of complementing party roles among different political parties emerged as impeding factor in development of democracy and its alternative political views. \n"+
  "lack of an informed society \n"+
  "The prevalence of weak political participation also hinders the expected development of democratization."
},
{
  id:39,
  question: " Constitution is",
  options: ["A fundamental or supreme law of the land.","A set of fundamental customs and traditions, rules and laws by which a government is organized","Any law which is made by the group of people","A and B are correct answers"],
  correct_option: "A and B are correct answers",
  explanation:'The constitution is both "A fundamental or supreme law of the land" and "A set of fundamental customs and traditions, rules and laws by which a government is organized.'
},
{
 id:40,
  question: "The control mechanism of the government organs in democratic system is___ ",
  options: ["Legitimacy ","Confidentiality","Check and balance","B and C are correct answers."],
  correct_option: "Check and balance",
  explanation:' In a democratic system, the control mechanism of government organs is primarily achieved through the concept of "check and balance,"'+ 
  " Where different branches of government (such as the executive, legislative, and judicial branches) have powers that check the powers of the other branches, ensuring that no single branch becomes too powerful."
},

{
  id:41,
  question: "A constitution to be rigid or flexible depend on____________",
  options: ["The complexity of amendment procedures","Government structure","Implementations","All are correct answers"],
  correct_option: "The complexity of amendment procedures",
  explanation: ''
},
{
  id:42,
  question: "The absence of constitutionalism will lead to:",
  options: ["Lawlessness","Arbitrary rules and power exercise","Absence of certainty","All are correct answers"],
  correct_option: "All are correct answers",
  explanation:""
},
{
  id:43,
  question: "Which one of the following countries is NOT an example for following a written constitution?",
  options: ["Great Britain","United states","Ethiopia","Nigeria"],
  correct_option: "Great Britain",
  explanation:"The United States, Brazil, Pakistan, Australia,Mexico, Switzerland, Canada, Nigeria, and"+
  " Ethiopia are among these countriesfollowing a written constitution."
},
{
  id:44,
  question: " ______is a form which requires simple procedure for amending the constitution.",
  options: ["Rigid constitution","Written constitution","Flexible constitution","Federal constitution"],
  correct_option: "Flexible constitution",
  explanation:'A "flexible constitution" is a form of constitution that allows for relatively simple procedures to amend or change it.'+ 
  ' a "rigid constitution," which typically requires complex and cumbersome procedures for amendments, a flexible constitution can be amended more easily and quickly.'
},
{
  id:45,
  question: "Among the following, which one is not the purpose of constitutionalism?",
  options: ["Ensuring sovereignty of the peoples.","Promotes the common good and national interest.","Make government officials accountable and responsive.","Impedes the democratization processes of a country."],
  correct_option: "Impedes the democratization processes of a country.",
  explanation:""
},
{
  id:46,
  question: "Civil and political rights are known as _______________",
  options: ["Liberty rights ","second generation rights","First generation right","A and B are correct answers"],
  correct_option: "First generation rights",
  explanation:"Liberty rights: These are often synonymous with civil and political rights but are not the specific term used to describe them."+
 " Second generation rights: These are economic, social, and cultural rights, which are distinct from civil and political rights."+
  " First generation rights: Civil and political rights are often referred to as first generation rights."
},
  {
  id:47,
  question: "Civil and political rights includes ",
  options: ["The Right to life","The Right to Privacy", "The Right to Security","All are correct answers"],
  correct_option: "All are correct answers",
  explanation:""
},
  {
  id:48,
  question: "All persons have the right to live in a clean and healthy environment.This right is known as _________________",
  options: ["solidarity right","First generation right","Third generation right","A and C are correct answers"],
  correct_option: "A and C are correct answers",
  explanation:"Solidarity right: This refers to rights that involve cooperation and mutual assistance among individuals and groups in society."+ 
  "The right to live in a clean and healthy environment can be considered a solidarity right as it involves the collective responsibility to ensure the well-being of the environment for the benefit of all."+
  "Third generation right: These are also known as collective rights or solidarity rights, and they include rights such as the right to development, the right to a clean environment, and the right to peace."
},
{
  id:49,
  question: "The UDHR considers _______ is fundamental right",
  options: [" The right to life","The right to respected",
  "The right to power","The right to security"],
  correct_option: "The right to life",
  explanation:"The Universal Declaration of Human Rights (UDHR) considers the right to life as a fundamental right."+
  " which states that Everyone has the right to life, liberty and security of person."+
  " Therefore, the UDHR recognizes the right to life as one of the fundamental human rights."
       
},
{
  id:50,
  question: "Governments have an affirmative duty to eliminate social inequalities and Provide opportunities for the exercise of human rights. Things stand out in this regard are :",
  options: ["Women’s right to equality","Least favored regions", "Children right to education","A and B are correct answers"],
  correct_option: "A and B are correct answers",
 explanation:""
},
{
  id:51,
  question: "The human rights statements enshrined in the Federal Democratic Republic of Ethiopia’s constitution were _______ by all regions,",
  options: ["Amended copy ","Direct copy or carbon copy","can be copied as necessary","heck dams"],
  correct_option: "Direct copy or carbon copy",
  explanation:"The human rights statements enshrined in the Federal Democratic Republic of Ethiopia’s constitution were directly copied or carbon copies by all regions."+ 
  " This means that the regions adopted the human rights provisions of the federal constitution without making significant changes."
},
{
id:52,
question: "In F.D.R.E constitution women right is indicated on ________",
options: ["Article 35 ","Article 36",
"Article 48","Article 49"],
correct_option: "Article 35",
explanation:"In the Federal Democratic Republic of Ethiopia's (F.D.R.E) constitution, women's rights are indicated in Article 35."+ 
" This article outlines the rights of women and emphasizes gender equality and non-discrimination."
},
{
id:53,
question: "Among the following which one is not the challenge of protecting human right in Ethiopia",
options: ["Poverty and inequality","Absence of regional constitution",
"Child labor abuse","Conflict and displacement"],
correct_option: "Absence of regional constitution",
explanation:""
},
{
  id: 54,
  question: " ________ a cultural and social practice whereby a widows required to marry a male relative of her late husband, often his brother",
  options: ["Intimidation","Uvulotomy"," Wife inheritance","Incision of eyelid "],
  correct_option: "Wife inheritance",
  explanation:"Wife inheritance is a cultural and social practice whereby a widow is required to marry a male relative of her late husband, often his brother."+ 
  "This practice is found in various cultures and societies around the world and is often associated with traditional customs and beliefs."
},
{
  id: 55,
  question: "Two people face each other and share their feelings, expectations, what they want and what they don’t want in order to find a solution. This conflict resolution mechanism is________",
  options: ["Negotiation","Mediation ","Arbitration","Litigation"],
  correct_option: "Mediation",
  explanation:"Mediation is a conflict resolution mechanism where two or more parties meet with a neutral third party, the mediator, to discuss their issues and work towards finding a mutually acceptable solution."+ 
  "In mediation, the parties face each other, share their feelings, expectations, and concerns, with the mediator facilitating the conversation and helping them reach a resolution."
},
{
  id: 56,
  question: "Formal method of resolving conflict in court in which the disputing parties appear before a judge, that is binding.",
  options: ["Negotiation ","Mediation","Arbitration","Litigation"],
  correct_option: "Litigation",
  explanation:"Litigation is the formal method of resolving a conflict in court in which the disputing parties appear before a judge. In litigation, the judge hears the arguments and evidence presented by both parties and makes a decision that is legally binding."
},
{
  id: 57,
  question: "Peace building process evolves",
  options: ["Before the occurrence of conflict","During the conflict happen",
  "After the conflict happen", "All are correct answers"],
  correct_option: "All are correct answers",
  explanation:""
},
{
  id: 58,
  question: "The importance of peace building are",
  options: ["Peace building prevents conflicts from escalating",
  "Peace building helps create security and stability",
  "Helps safeguard lives and properties","All are correct answer"],
  correct_option: "All are correct answer",
  explanation: ""
},
{
  id: 59,
  question: "In arbitration",
  options: ["Decisions are binding","Decisions are not binding","Arbitrator propose decision","A judge provides final decision"],
  correct_option: "Decisions are binding",
  explanation:""
},

{
  id: 60,
  question: "Among the following one is not the skill required from a good negotiation?",
  options: ["It requires the ability to compromise with others","It needs the ability to collaborate with others","Emphasizes the habit of aggression and selfishness","Requires farness from both sides of negotiator"],
  correct_option: "Emphasizes the habit of aggression and selfishness",
  explanation:""
},

]